<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	 version="5.0"
	 xml:id='guidelines'>
<info>
<title>DocBook Mailing List Guidelines</title>
<pubdate>07 Apr 2004</pubdate>
</info>

<para>This information<footnote><para>Credit where credit is due: I
stole the vast majority of this document from Tony Graham's excellent
posting on the DSSSL and XSL lists. Thanks, Tony!</para></footnote> is
posted to the DocBook and DocBook Applications mailing lists (and
their digests) at regular intervals under the subject line
<quote>DocBook list guidelines</quote>.</para>

<section><title>Posting</title>

<para>Only subscribers can post to mailing lists, and only from the
address they used when they subscribed. Mail from unsubscribed addresses
is forwarded to a moderator and may be forwarded after some delay. Note,
however, that due to the extraordinary volume of spam, some messages are
likely to get lost entirely.</para>

<para>Only text messages may be posted to the lists. If your mail
client posts using HTML or some other <quote>enriched</quote> format,
your message <emphasis>will be rejected</emphasis>. This decision was
motivated by the fact that the overwhelming majority of spam that gets
sent to the lists arrives as text/html.</para>

<para>There are two DocBook-related lists: docbook and docbook-apps.
The docbook list is for general questions about DocBook. The
docbook-apps list is for questions about applications (stylesheets,
transformation tools, publishing tools, processing requirements, etc.)
that use or work with DocBook.</para>

<para>Specifically:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Questions about DocBook markup (How do I markup a Widget? What's
a FuncSynopsisInfo for?) should be sent to the docbook list.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>Questions about XSL or DSSSL stylesheets, publishing DocBook
documents on your platform of choice, support for PostScript, PDF, or
other types of output, questions about Windows or Unix applications
that can consume or produce DocBook should be sent to the docbook-apps
list.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Do not begin your subject line with <quote>help</quote> or
<quote>subscribe</quote> since the list software will bounce the
message because it looks like is an administrative request.</para>

<para>Do not use un-informative subject lines like
<quote>Urgent</quote>, <quote>Easy question</quote>, or
<quote>Problem</quote>.  Instead, use a meaningful subject line that
will make sense to the people whose help you are trying to get.</para>

<para>Both subscribers to <email>docbook@lists.oasis-open.org</email> and
<email>docbook-digest@lists.oasis-open.org</email> should post their messages to
<email>docbook@lists.oasis-open.org</email>. The messages will be received by both
subscribers to the list and subscribers to the digest.</para>

<para>Both subscribers to <email>docbook-apps@lists.oasis-open.org</email> and
<email>docbook-apps-digest@lists.oasis-open.org</email> should post their messages to
<email>docbook-apps@lists.oasis-open.org</email>. The messages will be received by
both subscribers to the list and subscribers to the digest.</para>

<para>Do not start a new thread by replying to an unrelated message
and just changing the subject line since the header of your message
will contain references to the previous message and your new message
will appear in the archive as one of the replies to the original
message.  It is better to start a new message for a new thread.</para>

</section>

<section><title>Before You Post</title>

<orderedlist>
<listitem><para>Check that you are posting to the right list.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Make sure you are posting from the account that you
used to subscribe. If you post from another account, your message will
be delayed until it is approved by hand.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Check that your question isn't already answered in the
mailing list archives at <link xlink:href="http://lists.oasis-open.org/archives/docbook/">http://lists.oasis-open.org/archives/docbook/</link>
or <link xlink:href="http://lists.oasis-open.org/archives/docbook-apps/">http://lists.oasis-open.org/archives/docbook-apps/</link>.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>If you are replying to a post, trim the quoted
message to just the parts to which you are replying.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>The DocBook Technical Committee, as part of its commitment to
maintaining DocBook, responds to Requests for Enhancement (RFEs)
submitted by the DocBook user community. The likelihood that a
submitted RFE will be implemented is determined by the degree to which
it meets the following criteria:</para>

<orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
<listitem><para>The change is within the scope of the TC's charter.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>The change is consistent with the existing DocBook model.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>The change is beneficial to the community of users.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>The implication of criterion (c) is that if only one user or company
needs a particular change, the TC is likely to recommend a local
customization to acheive the desired result.</para>

</section>

<section><title>Replies Go to the Author</title>

<para>The DocBook lists don't set the <literal>Reply-to:</literal> header
on messages (see
<link xlink:href="http://www.unicom.com/pw/reply-to-harmful.html"><quote>Reply-To</quote> Munging Considered Harmful</link>)
so <emphasis>replies go to the author by default</emphasis>.  If you
want to reply to the list, make sure you include the list mailing
address in your reply.</para>

<para>Most mail readers make this easy by offering two forms of reply:
reply/group-reply or reply/follow-up, for example.  If you want to
post to the list, make sure you select group-reply or follow-up or
whatever your mail reader calls it.
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Use Short Quotes of Previous Messages in Replies</title>

<para>Please do not quote entire messages just to add a few lines at
the beginning or end.  Instead, quote the parts to which you are
directly replying or quote enough to establish the context.</para>

<para>Everybody on the list has already received the message that you
are quoting, and anyone searching the archive will find your message
and the previous message listed under the same thread.</para>

<para>Subscribers to the mailing list will just ignore most of the quoted
messages and move to the next post, but subscribers to the mailing
list Digest will mostly have to page past the quoted messages to reach
the next material in which they are interested in reading.</para>

</section>
<!--
<section><title>Do Not Post Attachments</title>

<para>Since mailing lists have in the past been unwittingly used for
spreading viruses in e-mail attachments, all e-mail attachments are
banned from the DocBook lists.</para>

<para>Most relevant documents (SGML and XML files, stylesheets,
documents, etc.) are text files, so this does not affect the majority
of posts to the list since you can include the files' text in the body
of your message.  If you need to refer to a binary file such as a PDF
document, you should put the file on a Web site or FTP site and
include the file's URL in your post.</para>

</section>
-->
<section><title>Cross-Posting</title>

<para>Cross-posting between the DocBook mailing lists or to other
lists is often counter-productive unless everybody who replies to the
thread is on both lists.  Cross-posts from non-subscribers continuing
the thread will bounce, and mailing list subscribers who are not also
on the other list will only see half of the thread, as will those on
the other list who are not also on the mailing list.  Subscribers to
both lists will see two copies of the message, annoying them as
well.</para>

</section>

<section><title>Subscribing and Unsubscribing</title>

<para>Subscriptions to the DocBook lists and their digest forms are
managed by OASIS: <link xlink:href="https://www.oasis-open.org/mlmanage/index.php"/>.
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Archive</title>

<para>The DocBook mailing list messages are archived at
<link xlink:href="http://lists.oasis-open.org/archives/docbook/">http://lists.oasis-open.org/archives/docbook/</link>.</para>

<para>The DocBook Applications mailing list messages are archived at
<link xlink:href="http://lists.oasis-open.org/archives/docbook-apps/">http://lists.oasis-open.org/archives/docbook-apps/</link>.</para>

</section>

<section><title>Reporting Bugs in Software</title>

<para>Confirmed bugs in software should be reported to its author
rather than to the mailing list, but it is appropriate to discuss
suspected bugs and workarounds on the docbook-apps list
<emphasis>only</emphasis>.</para>

</section>

<section><title>Further Information on DocBook</title>

<informaltable>
<tgroup cols="2">
<tbody>
<row>
  <entry><link xlink:href="https://www.oasis-open.org/docbook">http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook</link></entry>
  <entry>The DocBook Home Page</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><link xlink:href="http://www.docbook.org/">http://www.docbook.org/</link></entry>
  <entry>DocBook: The Definitive Guide</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><link xlink:href="http://docbook.sourceforge.net/">http://docbook.sourceforge.net/</link></entry>
  <entry><para>The DocBook project at SourceForge.</para>
<para>The recommended way to report bugs in software maintined in the
DocBook Project at SourceForge is with the project <quote>tracker</quote>
mechanism. Please be sure to attach a test case that demonstrates
the bug.</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><link xlink:href="http://nwalsh.com/docbook/xsl">http://nwalsh.com/docbook/xsl</link></entry>
  <entry>DocBook XSL Stylesheets</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>

</section>

<section><title>Contact</title>

<para>If you have any questions or problems, please contact Norman
Walsh, <email>ndw@nwalsh.com</email></para>

</section>
</article>
