<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	 version="5.0"
	 xml:id='custom-4x'>
<title>DocBook 4.x Customizations</title>

<toc/>

<para>The schemas described below are customizations of DocBook V4.x.
</para>

<section xml:id="simple">
<title>Simplified DocBook</title>

<para>This is a community project; it <emphasis>is not</emphasis> an
official product of the DocBook Technical Committee.</para>

<para>Over the years, the notion of a "simple" DocBook subset has come up
many times.  It has been observed that the number of elements in
DocBook can be a little overwhelming to the new user.
</para>

<para>Simplified DocBook is a small subset of DocBook.
The <link xlink:href="sdocbook/">online summary</link> shows just how
small this subset is.
</para>

<para>This DTD is an attempt to make a small subset of DocBook.
The goals of this subset are:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Documents written in the subset must be 100% legal DocBook
documents.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>This subset for single documents (articles, white papers, etc.),
so there's no need for books or sets, just 'articles'.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The markup should be the smallest practical subset, if you need
richly structured markup, use full DocBook. In
particular, the subset often selects a single element from a family of
related elements; for example, <tag>programlisting</tag> is
provided, but <tag>screen</tag> is not.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The DTD must work in online browsers (it's XML not SGML). It
must be small enough to download more-or-less painlessly.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<?schemas module='simple' release='4.*'?>
</section>

<section xml:id="forms">
<title>HTML Forms</title>

<para>This is a community project; it <emphasis>is not</emphasis> an
official product of the DocBook Technical Committee.</para>

<para>The “forms” schema adds HTML forms elements to DocBook.</para>

<?schemas module='htmlforms' release="4.*"?>

</section>

<section xml:id="mathml">
<title>MathML</title>

<para>This is an official product of the DocBook Technical Committee.</para>

<para>The “MathML” schema adds MathML elements to DocBook equations.</para>

<?schemas module='mathml' release="4.*"?>

</section>

<section xml:id="svg">
<title>SVG</title>

<para>This is an official product of the DocBook Technical Committee.</para>

<para>The “SVG” schema adds SVG elements elements to DocBook graphics.</para>

<?schemas module='svg' release="4.*"?>

</section>

<section xml:id="ebnf">
<title>EBNF</title>

<para>This is an official product of the DocBook Technical Committee.</para>

<para>The “EBNF” schema adds EBNF (Extended Backus-Naur Forms)
elements elements to DocBook.</para>

<?schemas module='ebnf' release="4.*"?>

</section>
</article>
